[English subtitles are available]
[본 영상은 한글자막을 제공합니다]
[ROAD HOME]
[귀로 : 너에게 돌아가는 길]
[Episode 8]
[제8화]
One year before the Spring Festival,
한 번은 춘절 전에
I participated in the bomb disposal,
폭발물을 처리해야 했는데
when my first love happened to be there.
그때 마침 내 첫사랑이 있었다
[2016]
[2016년]
It's the New Year's Gala after the meeting.
회의가 끝나면 새해 모임이 있을 거야
It looks like
올해는
we're gonna celebrate the New Year together.
함께 새해를 맞겠네
Yeah.
그러게
Captain Lu,
루 대장님
we found something suspicious
뒤뜰 휴지통 옆에서
by the trash can in the backyard.
수상한 물건을 발견했습니다
We've checked it with a detector,
탐지기로 확인해 보았는데
and there's something wrong.
의심 물질이 탐지되었습니다
Evacuate the crowd first.
먼저 사람들을 대피시켜
Yes, sir.
예
What happened?
무슨 일이지?
They said nothing about it.
아무런 설명이 없었어
Let's go out first.
일단 나가서 얘기하자
It might be a fire drill.
소방 훈련일 수도 있어
A bomb that explodes as the pressure on it is gone.
압력해제식 폭탄입니다
It has a simple structure.
구조는 간단합니다
A large part
폭탄의 내부 면적이
inside the bomb
매우 큰 것으로 보아
may hold clues about the perpetrator.
범인의 단서가 있을 수 있습니다
To protect these clues
단서를 보존하고
and trace the manufacturer,
제조자를 추적하기 위하여
I suggest on-site demolition.
이 자리에서 해제하는 걸 권합니다
The crowd has been evacuated.
시민들은 이미 대피했습니다
We agree on the on-site demolition.
이곳에서 해제하시죠
Sir,
경관님
what's going on inside?
안에 무슨 일 있습니까?
Nothing.
없습니다
Just a routine check.
규정에 따라 검사하는 겁니다
We're just waiting here.
계속 기다려야겠네
Why don't we take a walk around?
아니면 우리 근처를 돌아다닐까
It seems that...
마치…
According to my earlier search,
내가 전에 찾아봤는데
there's a rice noodle restaurant nearby
근처에 쌀국수 가게가 있었어
which is super famous.
엄청 유명해
How about this?
이건 어때?
Luosifen.
뤄쓰펀
Not bad.
좋지
Let's eat first.
먼저 밥부터 먹으러 가자
Let's go.
가자
The detonator is successfully removed.
기폭장치 제거 성공
Congratulations, guys.
축하합니다, 여러분
You can go back to celebrate the New Year.
빨리 돌아가 설을 보낼 수 있게 되었습니다
Did your first love know it?
첫사랑은 압니까?
Nope.
모른다
We had broken up at that time.
그때는 이미 헤어진 상태였다
Captain Lu,
루 대장님
what does your first love look like?
첫사랑은 어떻게 생겼습니까?
A couple of days ago,
엊그제
the test scores came out.
시험 점수가 나왔다
Yours was not high.
네 점수는 높지 않다
You shouldn't have asked about his first love.
그러게 루 대장님 첫사랑은 왜 묻냐?
I've made an appointment
담임선생님이랑
with the class adviser.
약속이 잡혔어
It's 3 p.m.
8일
on the 8th day of the first lunar month.
오후 3시
You come to pick me up first that day.
그날 나를 데리러 와
See you at 1 p.m.
우리 고모 집 밑에서
downstairs at my aunt's house.
오후 1시에 만나자
Are you in a relationship?
혹시 연애해?
You look distracted by your phone.
넋이 나간 채 핸드폰을 들고 있네
Nah.
아니에요
You look just like a single man.
딱 봐도 아내가 없어 보이십니다
Those in our team who have wives
우리 부대에서 아내가 있는 대원들은
always report their safety
다들 돌아오면
to their wives by phone when they come back.
핸드폰으로 아내에게 무사하다고 보고하죠
Or the wives will surely be mad when they return home.
그렇지 않으면 집에서 혼나니까요
[Lu Zheng Automobile Repair]
[루정 카센터]
Lu Chen,
루천
you are busier and busier
지금 일이
with your work now.
점점 바빠지는구나
You still work your socks off during the Spring Festival.
설을 쇠야 할 텐데 여전히 쉴 새 없이 일하네
The Spring Festival is the busiest time.
이때가 제일 바쁘죠
Go ahead.
가서 일 봐
You've had enough fun outside.
이 자식이 밖에서 충분히 놀았나 보네
And you still know to come back, huh?
집에 올 줄도 알고 말이야
Can I have a good talk
오늘 진지하게
with you today?
너와 대화를 나눌 수 있을까?
I just want you to get married
나는 그냥 네게 결혼을 하라고 한 거다
instead of doing
너에게
anything evil.
못 할 짓을 시킨 것도 아닌데
But do you have to
그럴 필요가 있냐?
treat me like this?
아비를 이렇게 대하고
You really embarrass me.
이렇게 내 체면을 깎아내리다니
How old are you?
나이가 몇인데
Are you gonna remain single forever?
평생 결혼 안 할 거냐?
Hey, Lu.
루 씨
He has been on duty for days before returning home.
아이가 며칠 동안 당직을 서고 돌아오기가
He worked so hard.
쉽지 않았을 거야
So did we!
누가 쉽겠어?
Did anyone
우린 어릴 때부터
ever take care of us in our childhood?
우리에게 신경 써 준 사람 있나?
I raised him with food,
먹고 마시는 것도 내 돈을 썼는데
but he doesn't listen to me when he has grown up.
컸다고 내 말을 안 듣는 게
Is that reasonable?
도리에 맞나?
You once served in the police force.
아직도 경찰직에 몸담고 있으니 망정이지
Filial piety is paramount among all virtues,
백 개의 선행 중에서 효도가 제일이니
and filial piety is everything.
효도하려면 모든 일을 거스르지 말아야지
Your father, who was a police officer,
경찰인 네 아버지가
also taught you a lot, right?
많이 가르쳐 줬을 거 아니냐
Why are you
어떻게 클수록
even more immature as you grow older?
점점 더 세상 물정을 모르냐?
Think carefully.
잘 생각해봐라
We still owe money to the Zhaos.
우리는 자오가에 돈을 빚진 상황이다
I'll pay them back.
자오가에서 빌린 돈은 제가 갚을 겁니다
You don't have to pay even a cent.
아버지 돈은 필요 없어요
D-Do you know
너
how much money we owe them?
얼마를 갚아야 하는지 아냐?
I know.
알아요
That's good.
네가 알고 있다니 됐다
I can do nothing to help.
나는 도와줄 수 있는 게 없어
You're pretty tough now.
너 이 자식 뭐 이리 무뚝뚝해
I knew it was worthwhile to bring my son up.
아들을 헛되이 키우지 않았구먼
Lu Chen,
루천
even if you
네가 내게
hold a great grudge against me,
큰 불만이 있다고 해도
you should come back for dinner once in a while.
별일 없으면 집에 와서 밥 먹어라
Your mom is still at home, anyway.
어쨌든 네 엄마가 아직 집에 있잖냐
Besides, I'm quite good
게다가 내 솜씨는
at cooking.
괜찮잖냐
Tell me what you wanna eat
언제 돌아올 거냐? 뭐 먹고 싶냐?
before you come back
미리 말해줘라
so that I can prepare in advance.
미리 준비해놓으마
Would you like something to eat?
밥 먹을래?
No.
안 먹어
Let me sleep for three hours first.
세 시간만 잘게
I have something else to do in the afternoon.
오후에도 일이 있어
Okay.
그래
Get me
정장 한 벌만
a formal suit
준비해줘
I'll wear it then.
일 처리할 때 입을 거야
You're going to see your future father-in-law.
예비 장인어른 뵈러 가는 거야?
Alright... I'll stop here.
됐어, 그만 말할게
Why are you so shy?
부끄러워하기는
Here, take it.
자, 받아
Let me think.
생각해 보자
I'll get you the most expensive one
제일 비싼 거로 찾아서
and iron it for you.
다림질해놓을게
I don't need the most expensive one.
그럴 필요 없어
Just gimme a medium-priced suit.
적당한 거면 돼
It's not your clothes.
형 옷도 아니잖아
So it's up to me.
내 맘대로 할 거야
Why did you come in a suit?
정장까지 입고 오다니
I'll meet Gui Xiao later.
이따가 구이샤오 만나러 가
No wonder.
여전히 이상한데
She came
자오민산이 대출 상환 계약서를
with the loan contract.
가지고 왔어
Go inside and sign it.
들어가서 사인하고
And then leave the rest to me.
남은 건 나한테 맡겨
Lu Chen.
루천
Can I
루천이랑 단둘이
talk to him alone?
얘기할 수 있을까요?
This time,
이번에는
I did something wrong.
내가 잘못한 게 있어
But I want to marry you
하지만 너와 결혼하고 싶은 건
sincerely.
진심이야
I've never ever
난 처음부터 끝까지
had any feelings for you.
너에게 어떤 감정도 없었어
This is the first time
졸업 이후에
we've met alone
우리도 처음으로
since our graduation.
단둘이 만나네
Xiaoshan,
샤오산 언니
Hai Dong and I...
저랑 하이둥은…
That was just a childhood thing.
다 어릴 때 일이지
It's meaningless to talk about it again.
더 이상 언급하지 말자
No matter what feelings
네가 루천에게
you have for Lu Chen,
어떤 생각을 하고 있던지
it's time to end them today.
오늘로 끝이야
Everyone knows what kind of person
루천 아버지가 어떤 사람인지
his father is.
모르는 사람이 없지
But Lu Chen grew up
하지만 루천은 어렸을 때부터
without wronging anyone,
누구에게도 미안한 일을 하지 않았어
and neither did he ever
자오민산, 너에게는 더욱
fail you, Zhao Minshan.
미안한 일을 한 적이 없지
From beginning to end,
처음부터 끝까지
you've been up to something.
네가 한 짓은 모두 정당하지 않잖아
That's the end of this affair.
이 일은 여기까지야
You two families
너희 두 집은
are no more than the creditor and the debtor.
빚을 졌고 갚는 사이야
If you still don't get it,
만약 잘 모르겠다면
I'll get even with you from that year.
난 너와 그 해부터 다시 계산할 거야
Get in.
차에 타
I don't have any formal clothes.
나는 격식 있는 옷이 없어서
So I'm wearing Hai Dong's suit.
하이둥 걸 입었어
Is it okay for me to meet the class adviser like this?
담임 선생님을 만나는 데 문제가 있을까?
Sure.
문제없어
It's my first time
네가 양복 입은 걸
seeing you in a suit.
처음 봐서
I feel kind of weird.
기분이 이상해
I'm not used to it, too.
나도 적응이 잘 안돼
This place is still the same as before,
여기는 예전과
without any change,
똑같네
Nothing has changed.
변함이 없지
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
Hello, I've heard a lot about you...
말씀 많이 들었습니다
Hello.
안녕하십니까
To get to know you,
저는 대장님을 알기 위해서
I've searched all over the Internet for your interviews.
인터넷에서 대장님의 인터뷰 기사를 검색했는데
What a pity that there's only one article.
아쉽게도 하나밖에 없더라고요
A great hero like you
대장님 같은 영웅들은
should be promoted more.
마땅히 널리 알렸어야 하는데요
Enough.
그만해
Sorry, Captain Lu.
죄송해요, 루 대장님
My husband
저희 남편이
just pretends to be passionate.
열정적인 척을 하네요
He's excited in front of others.
루 대장님이 오시니 괜히 흥분한 거예요
How can you say I pretend to be passionate?
열정적인 척이라니
This is my sister's first love.
우리 누나의 첫사랑인데
Let's get down to business first.
일부터 처리하자
Okay.
응
This class adviser
이 담임 선생님은
is an old teacher,
연세가 있으세요
who's very responsible.
책임감이 강하시죠
She specifically asked to meet
특별히 먼저
the Xiaonan's parents first
아이의 학부모를 만나
just to know the kid's
아이의
study and life conditions
학습 형편이나
and other things like personality.
성격 등을 알아보겠다고 하셨어요
I already called her
제가 미리 담임 선생님과
in advance,
전화해서
and told her the kid's parents
아이의 부모가
were not in Beijing.
베이징에 없다고 말씀드렸어요
Just go upstairs and feel free to talk to her.
올라가서 편하게 얘기하세요
Anyway, it's all for Xiaonan
어쨌든 아이가
to get used to the new school life
빨리 전학 생활에
as soon as possible.
적응하기 위해서잖아요
Okay, thank you.
네, 감사합니다
It's all my husband's fault.
모두 제 남편 때문이에요
I forgot to introduce myself.
제 소개를 드리는 것도 까먹었네요
My name is Xia Xia,
제 이름은 '샤샤'에요
and I'm Gui Xiao's sister-in-law.
구이샤오 언니의 사촌 올케죠
He is Wen Cheng,
제 남편 이름은 '원청'이고
Gui Xiao's cousin.
구이샤오 언니의 사촌 동생이에요
Let's go upstairs.
올라가자
Okay.
네
Gui Xiao's first love
언니의 첫사랑
is so handsome
너무 잘생겼다
with a good figure.
몸매도 좋아
That's enough...
됐어, 그만해
Do you think they still have a chance?
저 둘에게 아직 기회가 있을까?
I think so.
있을 것 같아
Coming.
나가요
Hello.
안녕하세요
Mom!
엄마
Mom, we have some guests.
엄마, 손님 오셨어요
Sister. brother-in-law, come here.
언니, 형부, 빨리 오세요
Come in, please. No need to change your shoes.
빨리 들어오세요, 신발은 갈아신지 않으셔도 돼요
Do you know her?
아는 사람이야?
Hello, Mrs. Sun.
쑨 선생님, 안녕하세요
Hello.
안녕하세요
This is Qin Xiaonan's uncle,
이분은 친샤오난의 삼촌
Lu Yanchen,
루옌천이에요
the one I mentioned to you
전화할 때
on the phone.
말씀드렸어요
He just came back from Qining.
샤오난 삼촌이 얼마 전에 치닝에서 돌아왔어요
Come in, please.
자, 들어오세요
Feel free to take your seats.
편하게 앉아요
Sister,
언니
he was the SWAT officer I talked about back then.
그때 말한 특수경찰이 바로 저 사람이야
Excuse me.
혹시
Were you a SWAT officer before?
특수경찰이셨어요?
Yes.
맞습니다
And so am I now.
지금도 그렇습니다
We thought you changed your job
양복을 입으신 걸 보고
when we saw you in a suit.
다른 일로 전향하신 줄 알았어요
Do I look familiar to you?
제 얼굴 아시겠어요?
It's normal that he doesn't know you.
널 모르시는 게 당연하지
Just a few years ago,
몇 년 전에
my sister and her classmate
제 여동생이 동창과
went on a graduation trip
졸업여행을 갔는데
and encountered bad weather,
악천후를 만나서
when we were trapped on the mountain, unable to get down.
하산할 수가 없었어요
Quite a lot of SWAT officers went to help us
많은 특수경찰이 와서
go down the mountain.
아이들이 산에서 내려올 수 있게 도와주셨어요
Do you remember that?
기억하시나요?
My classmate had straight hair,
제 친구는 생머리에
which was so long
허리까지 오는
to the waist.
긴 머리예요
I had curly hair,
저는 파마머리였어요
long brown and curly hair.
갈색으로 염색한 긴 파마머리요
I don't remember.
기억이 안 납니다
He carries out tasks every day.
저분이 매일 임무를 수행하시며
Who knows how many people
얼마나 많은 사람을 돕고
he has helped and saved?
구하시는데
You are just one of them.
넌 저분이 도운 국민 중 한 명이야
I just feel it's so rare.
나는 그냥 정말 대단하다고 생각했을 뿐이야
Thank you.
감사해요
Seriously.
정말로요
Thank you so much.
감사합니다
This is my duty,
제가 해야 할 일입니다
so don't mention it.
당연한 겁니다
Mom, here you are
여기요, 엄마
Here.
자
This is the winter vacation homework.
겨울 방학 숙제입니다
Bring it back.
가져가세요
Xiaonan doesn't have to finish it all.
아이가 다 할 필요는 없어요
I just want him to get used to
그냥
the mode
여기의
of our winter vacation homework.
겨울 방학 숙제 방식에 적응하고
Just help him assimilate first.
익숙해지자는 거죠
We'll leave Xiaonan to you
앞으로 샤오난을
from now on.
잘 부탁드리겠습니다
To quote your lines,
루 대장님의 말마따나
this is my duty,
이건 제가 해야 할 일이에요
so don't mention it.
당연한 거죠
Thank you.
감사합니다, 선생님
Do you really have no memory of it?
정말 기억이 안 나?
I remember the mission and the time,
임무와 시간은 기억나
but not the people.
사람은 기억 안 나
That mission came all of a sudden,
그 임무는 갑작스럽게 발생해서
and our entire team went there.
우리 사단 전체가 출동했었어
The squadron of police dogs
경찰견 중대도
was also searching for people everywhere on the mountain.
산을 오르내리며 사람을 찾았고
There were hundreds of tourists
당시 관광지의 관광객은
in the scenic back then,
수백 명의 배낭 여행객이었어
some of whom went really deep.
몇 사람은 산 깊이 들어가서
After several hours of search and rescue,
몇 시간 동안 수색하고 구조하려고
we searched all over the mountain.
온 산과 들판을 뒤졌는데
So I couldn't remember those faces at all.
기억나는 얼굴은 전혀 없어
High winds, hypothermia, the narrow mountain roads,
강풍이 불고 체온은 떨어지며 산길은 좁고
and a large number of tourists.
여행객은 많았지
In this case,
이런 상황에서
we had no time
우리는 절대 마음을 놓을 수 없는데
to care about
어떻게 사람의 이목구비를 신경 쓰고
different people's faces,
긴 머리인지
or whether it was the long hair or the curly hair.
파마머리인지 구분하겠어
You're right.
하긴 그렇네
When I was in high school,
고등학교 때
I often went shopping here.
여기에 쇼핑하러 자주 왔었어
In addition to this place,
여기랑
I also went to the clothing wholesale market
동물원 옆에 있는
next to the zoo.
의류 도매 시장에 자주 갔었어
One of my cousins was really good at bargaining.
사촌 여동생이 값을 잘 깎았어
Every time when I brought her out,
걔를 데리고 올 때마다
I could save a lot of money.
돈을 많이 아낄 수 있었지
The cousin you met today
오늘 네가 본 그 사촌 남동생은
was a follower when he was little.
어렸을 때부터 껌딱지처럼 우리를 따라다녔어
We didn't want to play with him.
우리는 모두 걔를 데리고 놀고 싶지 않았지
So he just cried and complained to others.
걔가 울면서 고자질했었어
Are these things
지금
unfamiliar to you
이런 것들을 보면서
now?
낯설다고 느끼지?
I haven't come back
고등학교 이후로
since high school.
돌아오지 않았어
During the years in Qining,
치닝에 있던 몇 년 동안
I've been back
베이징으로 돌아온 횟수는
less than five times.
다섯 번이 넘지 않을 거야
Actually, I don't know much
사실 지금 내게 베이징은
about today's Beijing
샤오난이 알고 있는 거와
just like Qin Xiaonan.
별 차이가 없어
Welcome home.
집으로 돌아온 걸 환영해
My brother's car is missing.
동생네 차가 안 보이네
The traffic is too congested.
너무 막혀서
We can't find them now.
지금 찾으려 해도 못 찾을 거야
Let's contact them when we get there.
도착하면 연락해
Actually, out of the only five times,
사실 다섯 번 중에
I did it twice to see you.
두 번은 널 보려고 왔었어
Why was it only once in my memory?
난 왜 한 번밖에 기억이 안 나지?
You came back
내가 대학에 입학했을 때
when I just went to college.
네가 왔었지
And when you asked to break up with me.
그리고 네가 헤어지자고 했을 때
Did you come back at that time?
그때 베이징에 왔었어?
I'm calling my brother
원청이 도착했는지
to see if they've arrived.
전화해 볼게
Call them in five minutes.
5분 후에 전화 걸어
OK.
응
The thing concerning Zhao Minshan
자오민산의 일은
is over.
마무리했어
You look so happy.
그렇게 좋아?
Of course.
당연히 좋지
Why didn't you tell me earlier?
왜 일찍 알려주지 않은 거야?
I had something serious to do with you this afternoon.
오후에 너와 처리해야 할 일이 있어서
So it was improper to talk about it.
말할 수 없었어
This is also a serious matter.
이것도 중요한 일이야
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
They've arrived.
애들 왔다
Let's get off.
빨리 내리자
Are you out of your mind again?
너 머리가 또 어떻게 된 거야?
I just subconsciously...
난 본능적으로, 난…
My sinful hand...
내 손이 문제네
Sister, I didn't recognize
누나, 방금은 저게
Chen's car just now.
천 형의 차인 줄 몰랐어
That's why I honked.
그래서 경적을 울린 거야
Never mind, but why are you so nervous?
울리면 울린 거지 뭘 그렇게 긴장하고 그래?
Let's go up from here.
가자, 여기서 올라가면 돼
Sister,
누나
are you going to
오늘 큰돈 쓰려고
spend a lot of money today、
마음먹었구나
Order whatever you want today.
오늘은 마음대로
It's on me.
먹고 싶은 거 시켜
Is there a budget limit?
금액 한도는?
A month's salary.
월급 한 달 치 금액이면
Is it enough?
충분할까?
I'll take a good look then.
그러면 내가 한번 잘 봐야겠네
Hello.
안녕하세요
We'd like to order this.
이거 하나 주세요
OK.
네
How much of this
이건 오늘은
do you have today?
양이 얼마나 되나요?
There's only one kilogram left.
오늘은 500g밖에 없습니다
That should be enough for four people.
그러면 네 명은 충분히 먹을 수 있겠네
I'll go check it with you later.
이따가 같이 한 번 가보자
Okay.
그래
And this one, too.
이것도 하나 주세요
The dishes here
이곳의 음식은
are all offered
모두 당일
at the day's supply price,
납품 가격으로 판매해요
just to keep them fresh.
새로운 걸 시도하는 거죠
Table 13.
13번 테이블
Check, please.
종업원, 계산해 주세요
Just a minute, sir.
고객님, 잠시만 기다려주십시오
Waiter, may I have the bill, please?
계산해 주세요
The gentleman who just left
방금 나간 남성분께서
has paid the bill.
이미 계산하셨어요
Could you please show me the bill?
명세서 좀 보여 주시겠어요
Okay, please hold on a moment.
네, 잠시만 기다려주세요
Hello, madam.
안녕하세요, 여사님
Captain Lu is quite generous!
루 대장님 경제력이 좋으시네요
Sister,
언니
your first love
언니 첫사랑이요
is from a rich family, right?
집안 형편이 좋은가 봐요
Waiter,
종업원
please pack
괜찮다면
the rest of the food for me.
남은 음식들 포장해 주세요
Okay.
알겠습니다
Thank you.
감사합니다
Get down to work.
일하자
This is the winter vacation homework
새 학교에서
assigned by your new school.
준 겨울 방학 숙제야
Although the teacher didn't ask you
선생님이 다 하라고
to finish it all,
하지는 않으셨지만
you still should do it all
요즘 너도 별일 없으니
since you're free recently.
다 해야 해
Don't slack off.
게으름 피우지 마
I'm going to dismantle some cars.
차 몇 대 분해하러 간다
Go to bed if you're sleepy.
졸리면 먼저 자
I'll sleep next door.
삼촌은 옆방에서 잘게
Some cars?
몇 대요?
I can only see him tomorrow morning indeed.
그럼 내일 아침에나 보겠네요
Luckily, your family
형네 집이
run a garage.
카센터를 해서 다행이네
There you are.
왔냐
The barbecue I ate was quite good.
이 꼬치가 맛있길래
So I've packed some for the kid.
샤오난 주려고 포장해왔어
You don't look like you're in trouble.
보아하니 일이 벌어진 것 같지는 않고
You look good!
안색도 아주 좋은데
Why are you dismantling the cars?
왜 차를 분해하는 거야?
I see.
알겠다
You disassemble cars whether you're happy
기분이 좋아도
or sad, right?
슬퍼도 차를 분해하는 거네, 그렇지?
Chen.
천 형
I just came back from a business trip,
지금 막 출장에서 돌아왔는데
and my brother told me you were transferred to Beijing.
우리 형한테 형이 베이징으로 전근해 왔다고 들어서
So I followed him to see you right away.
급하게 형을 보러 왔어요
Good.
좋네요, 형
You haven't changed a bit over the years.
몇 년이 흘렀는데 하나도 안 변했네요
You haven't changed either.
너도 마찬가지야
I just finished my homework.
방금 숙제 다 해서
I'm going to bed.
먼저 잘게요
Go ahead.
가서 자
Is he your kid, Chen?
천 형, 형 아이예요?
No.
아니
It's my friend's.
친구 아들
I thought you got married
형이 치닝에서
in Qining.
결혼한 줄 알았어요
Nah.
결혼은 무슨
He's waiting for Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 기다리고 있어
Stop talking nonsense.
무슨 헛소리야
Other people may have no idea about it,
다른 사람은 몰라도
but I know.
난 알아
Gui Xiao in our class?
우리 반 그 구이샤오?
Of course. Who else can it be?
당연하지, 그러면 누구겠냐?
Chen and Gui Xiao were once in a relationship?
천 형이랑 구이샤오가 사귀었다고?
They
얘네 둘은
fell in love after graduation.
졸업 이후에 사귀었는데
Many people don't know that.
사람들은 잘 몰라
Why didn't you tell me?
아니, 왜 나한테 말 안 해줬어?
Why should I tell you?
알려줘서 뭐 하냐?
What are you looking at?
뭘 봐
Pour Chen a drink.
천 형한테 술 따라줘
No.
안 마셔
It's my shift tomorrow afternoon, so I can't drink.
내일 오후 근무라 못 마셔
Don't drink directly with the bottle.
입대고 마시지 마
How can I drink it in this case?
네가 이러면 내가 어떻게 마시냐?
Pour it into the glass.
잔에 따라 마셔
Help yourself.
네 건 네가 따라
I'm so happy to see Chen.
천 형 만나서 너무 기쁘네요
Here you are, Chen.
천 형, 받으세요
I won't drink.
난 안 마셔
He already said that.
안 마신다고 했잖아
Thank you.
감사해요, 형
I'm fine.
괜찮아요, 형
Go continue to talk to my brother.
가서 우리 형이랑 계속 얘기해요
Thank you, Chen.
천 형, 고마워요
Leave him alone.
내버려 둬
Just let him throw up.
토하게 놔줘
He'll be fine after that.
토하고 나면 괜찮을 거야
Come back and sit.
이리 돌아와서 앉아
Sit.
앉아
His condition
쟤가 이러고 있는 걸 보니
reminds me of my past.
그때가 생각나네
When Meng Xiaoshan got married,
멍샤오산이 결혼하던 그날
I almost
하마터면
drank to death in front of their house.
걔네 집 앞에서 술 마시고 죽을 뻔했어
And in the next half a year,
그 후 반년 동안
I shed all my tears
반평생 흘릴 눈물을
of half my life.
다 흘렸어
Have you ever cried
울어본 적 있어?
for Gui Xiao?
구이샤오 때문에
It also counts if you cried secretly.
몰래 운 것도 포함해서
Have you cried for her?
그런 적 있어?
What are you doing?
뭐 하는 거야?
Since you already said it,
말 나온 김에
just finish the story.
그냥 다 말해봐
She wanted to break up with me.
구이샤오가 헤어지자고 했고
I called her over and over again.
나는 구이샤오에게 몇 번이고 전화했는데
She hung up every time.
계속 전화를 끊었어
She didn't even let me
조금이라도 말할
say anything.
시간을 주지 않았지
Then I didn't dare to call her.
나중에는 전화할 수 없었어
I was afraid she would be scolded by her family if I called too many times.
전화를 많이 하면 구이샤오가 집안 어른들께 혼날까 봐 걱정됐어
Half a year after our breakup,
헤어지고 반년 후에
[2012]
[2012년]
I finally had a chance to return to Beijing.
드디어 베이징으로 돌아갈 기회가 생겼어
And I had to leave the next day.
다음 날 바로 돌아가야 했지
That night,
그날 밤
she still refused to meet me.
구이샤오는 여전히 날 만나려 하지 않았어
I didn't go home.
난 집에 가지 않고
I stayed at the train station until dawn,
동틀 무렵까지 기차역에 있다가
and then left directly.
바로 돌아갔지
I'm in Beijing.
나 베이징에 있어
Let's go out to meet.
얼굴 좀 보여줘
♫You gradually feel nothing about my sharing♫
♫ 내가 쏟아내는 말에 넌 점점 무감각해지고 ♫
♫Hang on to coldness♫
♫ 억지로 버티다 보니 다소 냉담해졌지 ♫
Forget about it.
됐어
♫I can't say good night♫
♫ 보내지 못 한 '잘 자'라는 인사 ♫
♫I once believed hard work would leave no regrets♫
♫ 노력하면 후회가 없다고 믿었어 ♫
♫But the ending is too bad♫
♫ 하지만 이 끔찍한 결말을 ♫
♫Who will shoulder it for me?♫
♫ 누가 나 대신 감당해줄까 ♫
♫We said it would last forever♫
♫ 우리 영원히 변치 말자고 했지만 ♫
♫But we were separated in the end♫
♫ 결국 헤어졌고 ♫
♫I wait until I give up all resistance♫
♫ 지금 흘러가는 시간을 버티며 ♫
♫Let time pass by♫
♫ 천천히 기다려왔지 ♫
♫Never thought that love♫
♫ 생각지도 못했어, 사랑이 ♫
♫Is not about the trials and tribulations♫
♫ 시련을 겪는 것처럼 ♫
♫Not that easy♫
♫ 간단하지 않을 줄은 ♫
♫Let's wait until the turn♫
♫ 우리 시나리오의 반전이 있길 기다리자 ♫
♫Still have expectations♫
♫ 아직 희망은 남아있어 ♫
♫In the night without you♫
♫ 네가 없어도 ♫
♫I can't shed a tear♫
♫ 눈물도 흘리지 않는 밤에 머물러 있어 ♫
♫Street lights on the corner and the darkness I passed by♫
♫ 모퉁이의 가로등 불빛은 어둡고 ♫
You came back after you broke up, huh?
헤어진 후에 베이징으로 왔었다고?
♫Everything's too late♫
♫ 모든 게 너무 늦었어 ♫
I know you're single-minded.
형이 한결같다는 걸 알아
But I didn't expect
그런데 구이샤오에 대한
you to have such deep feelings for Gui Xiao.
감정이 이렇게 깊은 줄은 몰랐네
I should go back.
이만 가봐야겠다
Wake up.
일어나
Let's go.
가자
I'll pick up Qin Xiaonan tomorrow.
내일 친샤오난 데리러 올게
I have to send Hai Jianfeng back first.
일단 하이젠펑 돌려보내야 해
His mom really loves him.
얘네 엄마의 보물이야
If he doesn't return in the middle of the night,
한밤중인데 돌아가지 않으면
she'll scold either him or me.
얘가 아니고 날 혼낼 거야
See you.
간다
Go ahead.
가 봐
Chen,
천 형
wish you two all the best.
둘이 행복해야 해요
Did you buy it?
삼촌이 산 거예요?
Who else could it be other than me?
나 말고 또 누가 있겠어?
Aunt Gui Xiao, of course!
구이샤오 이모요
You're not related to her.
구이샤오랑 아무런 관계도 아닌데
Dare you take it at will?
뻔뻔하게 옷을 받은 거야?
No.
미안하죠
So,
그래서
I'm writing it down.
장부에 적어놨어요
When I make money,
나중에 제가 돈을 벌면
I'll take inflation into account
물가 상승도 감안해서
and pay her back together.
전부 갚아야죠
Good.
그런대로 괜찮네
But remember,
하지만 기억해
you need skills to pay her back.
돈을 갚는 기술도 있어야 해
Don't break her heart.
구이샤오의 마음을 상하게 해서는 안 돼
Of course.
당연하죠
Let me see.
한번 보자
You're about to be as handsome as me.
내 반절쯤 멋있네
What a narcissist.
잘난 척하기는
I can't buy you clothes of really good brands
2년 동안 돈을 모았는데
since I've been saving money these years.
좋은 브랜드 옷을 사줄 수가 없네
But,
하지만
new clothes for Chinese New Year.
설에는 새 옷이 있어야 한다
This is the custom.
이게 규칙이야
I know.
알겠어요
Let's go and eat.
가자, 밥 먹자
[Xie's Special Beef Noodles]
[라오셰 특제 우육면집]
This is your Aunt Gui Xiao's
여기는 구이샤오 이모가
favorite restaurant
학교 다닐 때
when she was a student.
제일 좋아하는 식당이었어
I want to eat what she likes.
이모가 늘 먹던 거 먹을래요
Is this your son?
아들입니까?
No.
아닙니다
My nephew.
제 조카예요
I thought you got married
그 아가씨랑
with that girl and had this kid.
결혼해서 낳은 아들인 줄 알았습니다
Which girl?
어떤 아가씨요?
You know what?
넌 모를 거다
Your uncle
네 삼촌이
always brought that girl
옛날에 그 아가씨를 데리고 자주
to eat noodles here before.
국수를 먹으러 왔었지
She looked so pretty,
아주 예쁘게 생겼는데
and was really good at eating spicy food.
매운 걸 엄청 잘 먹었지
She ate one bowl of noodles
국수 한 그릇 먹는데
with half a bottle of spicy sauce.
매운 소스를 반절 가까이 넣어 먹었어
It was summer,
한여름에는
and even I was sweating when I saw her eating.
그 아가씨가 먹는 것만 봐도 내가 땀이 났었지
Same as usual.
늘 먹던 걸로
Two bowls.
두 개 주세요
Okay.
알았습니다
Just a moment.
기다려주세요
What?
왜?
Don't you want to take the chance
설을 쇠는 김에
of the Spring Festival
구이샤오 이모랑
to invite Aunt Gui Xiao to hang out?
놀러 가고 싶지 않아요?
Mind your own business
어른들의 일을
instead of ours.
네가 신경 쓸 바야?
Were it not for
내가
Aunt Gui Xiao,
구이샤오 이모의 체면을 봐주지 않았다면
I wouldn't care about you.
삼촌을 신경이나 썼을까요
Here are your noodles.
국수 나왔습니다
Enjoy your meal.
맛있게 드세요
Thank you.
감사합니다
Are you busy?
바빠?
I'm off today.
오늘 쉬는 날이야
Are you...
그러면 너…
How is Qin Xiaonan doing?
친샤오난은 잘 지내?
He said
샤오난이
he missed you.
네가 보고 싶대
Me too.
나도 그래
I'll take him to see you.
샤오난을 데리고 널 보러 갈까?
Don't bother.
아냐
I'll go to meet him,
내가 갈게
and visit Meng Xiaoshan by the way.
마침 멍샤오산도 봐야 해
Your reward.
상이야